James M. Crawford Papers 1906-1988 Mss.Ms.Coll.66
American Philosophical Society
James M. Crawford Papers
1906-1988
Mss.Ms.Coll.66
American Philosophical Society
68.75 Linear feet
James M. Crawford was a linguist who mainly studied Native American languages, including Cocopa, Yuchi, and Mobilian trade language. He came to the field of linguistics halfway through his lifetime after pursuing a career in forestry in the West and Southwest. After receiving his PhD in 1966 from the University of California at Berkeley, he returned to his birthplace, Georgia, where he taught in the Department of Linguistics at the University of Georgia at Athens. The collection is organized into seven series: I. Correspondence, 1964-1986; II. Subject Files, 1949-1987; III. Works by Crawford, 1962-1986; IV. Research NOtes & Notebooks, 1906-1988; V. Card Files, 1960s-1980s; VI. Course Material, 1961-1986; VII. Photographs, 1963-1978.
68.75 linear feet
Crawford, James Mack, 1925-1989
Biographical/Historical note
James M. Crawford was born on 18 September 1925 in Commerce, Georgia, where his father was a farmer. As a child, Crawford became interested in languages by listening to Mexican radio stations; while in school, he studied Latin, French, and German. He served in the United States Army in Europe from 1943 to 1946 during the second World War. After returning to Georgia, he studied forestry at the University of Georgia in Athens, receiving his B.S. in 1949.
From 1949 to 1950, Crawford worked as County Ranger in the Georgia Forestry Commission in Butler, Georgia; then from 1950 to 1952 as Forester in the United States Forest Service in California, Arizona, and New Mexico. From 1953 to 1954, Crawford worked as Lumber Grader for the Hammond Lumber Company in Samoa, California and then for a year as Surveyor for the Utah Construction Company in Hawthorne, Nevada.
In 1956, Crawford returned to the forestry profession as Research Forester at the Pacific Southwest Forest and Range Experiment Station in Berkeley, California, where he worked until 1961. While there, he encountered a linguist working in the Sierras and became fascinated with the study of languages as a career. Soon after this encounter, Crawford arrived as a graduate student at the Department of Linguistics of the University of California at Berkeley, beginning his linguistic studies with Russian and Old Slavic. One of his professors, Dr. Mary Haas (a student of Edward Sapir), encouraged Crawford to study Native American languages, and he became engrossed in the intricacies of Cocopa, Yuchi, and Choctaw. From 1962 to 1965, he was a teaching assistant at Berkeley.
Crawford's dissertation, The Cocopa Language, focused on the language of the Cocopa Indians, whom he had visited in 1962 in Arizona. Cocopa is one of ten Yuman languages spoken in Arizona, California, and Mexico. In a later work, Cocopa Texts (1983), Crawford published phonetic transcriptions and English translations of Cocopa stories that he had collected.
Crawford received his Ph.D. in 1966. That year, he became Assistant Professor in the Department of Anthropology at Idaho State University, where he taught for two years. He returned in 1968 to the University of Georgia, this time as Associate Professor in the Department of Anthropology; in 1981, he became Professor. Crawford taught courses in linguistics, phonology, morphology and syntax, field methods in linguistics, and Native American languages.
Crawford received a grant from the American Council of Learned Societies in 1976 to study Mobilian trade language (a now extinct language that was once spoken along the Mississippi River). He won the 1977 James Mooney Award, given jointly by the Southern Anthropological Society and the University of Tennessee Press, for his manuscript, The Mobilian Trade Language, which was judged to be the outstanding manuscript on New World cultures. As part of the award, the manuscript was published by the University of Tennessee Press. During his field work, Crawford had traveled to Louisiana to interview the remaining three speakers of Mobilian; they had all died by the time the book was published.
Crawford also received grants to study Yuchi, which is a language isolate; that is, it is not related to other known languages and contains few borrowed words. The Yuchi Indians lived throughout South Georgia before being moved to Oklahoma with the Creek Indians in the 1830s. The Yuchi dictionary that Crawford worked on was never published. Crawford also helped to show that Yuchi Indians had been present in the Georgia area one hundred years sooner than had been previously thought. When Kristian Hvidt, librarian of Danish Parliament in Copenhagen, Denmark, discovered in 1977 some drawings of Yuchi Indians that had been done by Baron Philipp Georg Friedrich von Reck in the 1730s, Crawford was able to translate the Yuchi text on the labels.
Crawford received other grants to study Alabama, Cherokee, and other southeastern Indian languages. In 1980, he received, from the University of Georgia, the Albert Christ-Janer Award for Creativity in Research.
Crawford organized several symposia on Southeastern Indian Languages, and in 1978, he co-organized with Robert L. Rankin the first Conference on Muskogean Languages and Linguistics at the University of Oklahoma in Norman. He served as referee for the International Journal of American Linguistics, Macmillan Publishing Company, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, and the Wenner-Gren Foundation. He edited the Department of Anthropology newsletter.
Crawford was a member of the American Anthropological Association, the Arizona Historical and Archaeological Society, the International Linguistics Association, the Linguistic Society of America, the Pacific Coast Archaeological Society, the Southeastern Conference on Linguistics, and the Southern Anthropological Society.
Crawford's publications include numerous articles and reviews, as well as Studies in Southeastern Indian Languages, a book that he edited. He also published a Cocopa Dictionary as a companion volume to Cocopa Texts. Crawford was in the process of writing a Cocopa grammar that would be the third volume in the series on the Cocopa language when he died on 5 May 1989.
Scope and Contents note
The James M. Crawford Papers (1906-1988) contain correspondence, subject files, manuscripts of published and unpublished works by Crawford, research notes by Crawford, course material, and photographs, which document Crawford's career as a linguist.
The papers (113 boxes; 68.75 linear feet) are divided into seven series:
Series I. Correspondence 1964-1986 (1 box;.25 linear feet)
Series II. Subject Files 1949-1987 (2 boxes;.5 linear feet)
Series III. Works by Crawford 1962-1986 (18 boxes; 8 linear feet)
Series IV. Research Notes & Notebooks 1906-1988 (10 boxes; 4.75 linear feet)
Series V. Card Files 1960s-1980s (83 boxes; 54 linear feet)
Series VI. Course Material 1961-1986 (3 boxes;.75 linear feet)
Series VII. Photographs 1963-1978 (1 box;.25 linear feet)
Series III-IV. Oversized (1 box;.25 linear feet)
Oversized materials follow the same series arrangement as noted above. Cross referencing to oversized material appears on the folders in the standard sized boxes. Reprints have been moved to the printed materials collection of the APS library. To retrieve reprints, consult the card catalog for printed materials. Sound recordings have also been removed from the collection and cataloged as Recording 184.
Related Archival Materials
Audio recordings made and collected by Crawford are available in the Recordings of Native American languages collection (Mss.Rec.184).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Crawford Papers were donated to the APS Library by Elisabeth Crawford in 1990 (Accession #1990-2551ms). Six Cocopa notebooks (three from 1978, three from 1979) were donated by Margaret Langdon in 1994 (Accession #1994-690ms).
General note
During processing, the collection was re-foldered and re-housed in acid-free folders and boxes. Metal fasteners were removed and replaced with plastic clips when necessary. A separate listing of torn or severely deteriorated manuscripts and manuscripts that need to have glue and tape removed has been compiled by series and submitted to the Conservation Department.
All newspaper clippings were photocopied onto acid-free paper; the original clippings were then discarded. Other brittle or torn items were also photocopied, and when considered valuable, were retained. Photographs have been interleaved with non-buffered, acid-free paper.
Hayes, Lillian; Hayes, Victor; Keyaite, Ilona Mae; Alabama language; American Council of Learned Societies; Catawba language; Choctaw language; Cocopa language; Drafts (preliminary versions).; Field notes.; Gelatin silver prints; Kiliwa language; Linguists; Manuscripts (for publication); Mobilian trade language; National Science Foundation; Newari language; Nitrate negatives; Notebooks; Photoprints; Portrait photographs; Reviews (Criticism); Wolof language; Yavapai language; Yuchi language
- Series I. Correspondence, 1964-1986
  Scope and Contents note
  contains mainly incoming letters, although there are a few carbons of letters written by Crawford. Most of the letters are photocopies. The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name and then chronologically within each folder. Enclosed manuscripts have been removed from this series and placed in Series III. A photocopy of the title page was filed with the original letter. Most of the correspondence deals with Crawford's publications. There is one letter from a Native American informant, Ilona Mae Keyaite.
  - Ferguson, Charles A., 1973 (Box Series I: F - V)
  - Good, Dwight, 1965
  - Handbook of North American Indians, 1983
  - International Journal of American Linguistics, 1975, 1977
  - Journal of California Anthropology, 1978
  - Keyaite, Ilona Mae, 1964
  - Linguistic Society of America, 1970-1973
  - McDavid, Ravin L., Jr., 1970
  - Munro, Pamela, 1986
  - Pulte, William, 1972
  - Richardson, Miles, 1976
  - Sawyer, Jesse O., 1969
    -See also Ser.III-A, "Meaning in Cocopa Auxiliary Verbs"
  - Southern Anthropological Society, 1967, 1969
  - Sturtevant, William C., 1977-1978
  - University of California Press, 1981
  - University of Georgia, 1971-1980
  - The University of North Carolina, 1978
  - University of South Florida, 1974
  - The University of Tennessee Press, 1978
  - Voegelin, Charles F., 1970
- Series II. Subject Files, 1975-1982
  includes grant applications and information for the American Council of Learned Societies and the National Science Foundation, clippings about Crawford and his work, copies of Crawford's curriculum vitae, reviews of Crawford's books, and two plant specimens collected by Crawford. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title, and then chronologically within each folder.
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1975-1982 (Box Series II: A - So)
  - Bilingual Education, 1974-1975
  - Clippings, 1964-1984
  - The Cocopa Language, [1967]
  - Cocopa Texts, 1982-1983
  - Cocopah Indian Reservation Map, 1949
  - Conference on Muskogean Languages and Linguistics, 19 Oct. 1978
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1966-1987
  - Informants' Receipts, 1978
  - The Mobilian Trade Language-- Reviews, 1979-1981, n.d.
  - National Science Foundation
    - Folder #1, 1969-1970
    - Folder #2, 1971-1973
  - "Plant Collected at Maggie Poncho's Alabama-Cereshalta[?] Reservation, Texas", Aug. 1970
  - "Plant Collected Near Clarkdale, Arizona", 13 Jul. 1967
  - Sapulpa, Oklahoma Public Schools, 4 Jun. 1977
  - Southern Anthropological Society, 1971
  - Studies in Southeastern Indian Languages-- Readers' Reviews, [1971] (Box Series II: St - U)
  - Studies in Southeastern Indian Languages-- Reviews, 1975-1979
  - University of Georgia Grant Proposal, 1982-1983
- Series III. Works by Crawford, 1962-1986
  contains handwritten and typed notes, outlines, drafts, and final versions of articles, books, and reviews. This series is arranged alphabetically by title. For some works, the notes, drafts, and final copies are filed together. This series is divided into four subseries that reflect the subject content of the works: A. Cocopa, B. Yuchi, C. Yuman, and D. Other. The first subseries, Cocopa, includes Crawford's dissertation, The Cocopa Language and notes, drafts, and final versions of his book, Cocopa Texts. The second subseries, Yuchi, includes "Reconnaissance among Several Indian Groups in Mississippi, Oklahoma, Texas, and Louisiana" and "Yuchi Text with Translation." The third subseries, Yuman, includes "Account of Reconnaissance among Several Languages of the Yuman Family in Arizona." The fourth subseries, Other, includes some papers that Crawford wrote for graduate courses at the University of California at Berkeley; notes, drafts, and final versions of his books, The Mobilian Trade Language and Studies in Southeastern Indian Languages; and reviews of other people's books.
  - Series III-A. Works by Crawford--Cocopa, 1962-1986
    - "Baby Talk in an American Indian Language", 1974 (Box Series IIIA: B - Cocopa Dict. #2)
    - "Classificatory Verbs in Cocopa", 1986
      -See also Ser.I, Munro, Pamela
    - "Cocopa I", 1975; 2 Folders
      -See also Ser.III-A, "A Cocopa Tale: The Alligator Who Couldn't Turn Over"
    - "The Cocopa Auxiliary Verb ya "Be Located, Happen" ", [1969]
    - "Cocopa Baby Talk", [1969]
      -See also Ser.I, Southern Anthropological Society
    - Cocopa Dictionary, [198-]
      - Folder #1-2
      - Folders #3-9 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Dict. #3-9)
      - Folders #10-16 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Dict. #10-16)
      - Folders #17-23 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Dict. #17-23)
      - Folders #24-27 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Dict. #24 - Cocopa Lang.--Ms. #2)
    - Cocopa Dictionary-- Disks
      -See Oversized
    - "Cocopa Grammar", [1973]
    - The Cocopa Language-- Ms., 1966
      - Folders #1-2
      - Folders #3-5 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Lang.--Ms. #3 - Cocopa Lang.--Notes #4)
    - The Cocopa Language-- Notes, 1966
      - Folders #1-4
      - Folder #5 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Lang.--Notes #5 - Cocopa Texts #5)
    - "The Cocopa Language: Thematic Prefixes of the Verb", May 1965
    - "A Cocopa Tale: The Alligator Who Couldn't Turn Over", [1976]
      -See also Ser.III-A, "Cocopa I"
    - Cocopa Texts, [1983]
      - Folders #1-5
      - Folders #6-11 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Texts #6-11)
      - Folders #12-15 (Box Series IIIA: Cocopa Texts #12 - Ma)
    - "Coyote and His Daughter", [1978]
    - "Epenthetic Vowels in Cocopa Phonology", [1967]
    - "Linguistic Color Categorization in Mesamerica: Instructions for Descriptive Field Work", [1978]
    - "A Look at Some Cocopa Auxiliaries", [1972]
    - "Maricopa and Cocopa: A Binary Comparison", Dec. 1962
    - "Meaning in Cocopa Auxiliary Verbs", [1968]; 2 Folders (Box Series IIIA: Me - U)
      -See also Ser.I, Sawyer, Jesse O.
    - "More on Cocopa Baby Talk", [1977]
    - "The Morphology of the Cocopa Noun", May 1964
    - "Nominalization in Cocopa", 1978
      -See also Ser.IV-A, "Relativization and Nominalization in Cocopa"
    - "A Preliminary Report on the Phonemes of the Cocopa Language", Apr. 1963
    - "Proto-Yuman: Reconstructed from Cocopa, Diegueño, Maricopa, and Yavapai"
      -See Ser.III-C, same title
    - "Spanish Loan Words in Cocopa", [1979]
      -See also Ser.I, Journal of California Anthropology
    - "Uses and Functions of Cocopa Auxiliary Verbs"
  - Series III-B. Works by Crawford--Yuchi, 1969-1979
    - "Biloxi, Ofo, and Yuchi", [1970] (Box Series IIIB: B - Yuchi Phonology #1)
    - "Reconnaissance Among Several Indian Groups in Mississippi, Oklahoma, Texas, and Louisiana", Aug. 1969; 2 Folders
    - "Timucua and YuchI. Two Language Isolates of the Southeast", [1977]; 2 Folders
    - "Yuchi", n.d.
    - "Yuchi" in Handbook of North American Indians, [1979]; 2 Folders
    - "Yuchi Phonology", [197-]
      - Folder #1
      - Folders #2-3 (Box Series IIIB: Yuchi Phonology #2 - Yuchi T.)
    - "Yuchi Text with Translation", [1972]
  - Series III-C. Works by Crawford--Yuman, 1962-1980
    - "Account of Reconnaissance Among Several Languages of the Yuman Family in Arizona", 1962 (Box Series IIIC: A - S)
    - "Bibliography of the Tribes and Languages of the Yuman Family"
    - Cochimi and Proto-Yuman: Lexical and Syntactic Evidence for a New Language Family in Lower California by Mauricio J. Mixco--Review, [1980]
    - "A Comparison of Chimariko and Yuman", [1976]
    - "Proto-Yuman: Reconstructed from Cocopa, Diegueño, Maricopa, and Yavapai", Jan. 1964
    - "Some Cognate Sets from Chimariko and Several Yuman Languages"
  - Series III-D. Works by Crawford--Other, 1962-1986
    - "The Brahui Verb: A Restatement of the Morphology", 1964; 2 Folders (Box Series IIID: Bra - Bri)
    - "A Brief Account of the Indian Tribes of Northeast Georgia", 23 Feb. 1962
    - The Caddoan, Iroquoian, and Siouan Languages by Wallace L. Chafe; A Grammar of Biloxi by Paula Ferris Einaudi; A Grammar of Pawnee by Douglas R. Parks; and Wichita Grammar by David S. Rood--Review, 1977 (Box Series IIID: C - Mobilian Tr. Lang.--Ms. #3)
    - Dictionary of Indian Tribes of the Americas-- Articles, [1979]
    - "English Sun and Latin Sol", Dec. 1962
    - A Grammar of Diegueño Nominals by Larry Paul Gorbet--Review, [1978]
    - A Grammar of Diegueño, the Mesa Grande Dialect by Margaret Langdon-Review, [1972]
    - "Hokan and Siouan Words for Mouth", [1070-1971]; 2 Folders
    - Houma
      -See Ser.III-D, Dictionary of Indian Tribes of the Americas-- Articles
    - Kiliwa Dictionary by Mauricio J. Mixco--Review, [1986]
    - Mobile
    - The Mobilian Trade Language-- Ms., [1978]
      - Folders #1-3
      - Folders #4-9 (Box Series IIID: Mobilian Tr. Lang.--Ms. #4-9)
      - Folders #10-11 (Box Series IIID: Mobilian Tr. Lang.--Ms. #10 - Mobilian Tr. Lang.--Notes #5)
    - The Mobilian Trade Language-- Notes, [1978]
      - Folders #1-5
      - Folder #6 (Box Series IIID: Mobilian Tr. Lang.--Notes #6 - Studies in S.I. Lang. #2)
    - Natchez
    - The Natchez: Annotated Translations from Antoine Simon le Page du Pratz's Histoire de la Louisiane and a Short English-Natchez Dictionary by Charles D. Van Tuyl--Review, [1981]
    - "Native Americans and Their Languages" by Roger Owen--Review, [1978]
    - "The Nature of Language: The View of Linguists", May 1964
    - Nez Perce Texts by Haruo Aoki--Review, [1980]
    - "On the Relationship Between Timucua and Muskogean", [1986]
    - A Papago Grammar by Ofelia Zepeda--Review, [1984]
    - "A Phonological Comparison of the Speech of Two Communities in California: East Bay and El Centro", Jan. 1964
    - "The Phonological Sequence ya in Words Pertaining to the Mouth in Southeastern and Other Indian Languages", [1975]
    - Quapaw
    - Studies in Southeastern Indian Languages, [197-]
      - Folders #1-2
      - Folder #3 (Box Series IIID: Studies in S.I. Lang. #3)
- Series IV. Research Notes, 1962-1988
  contains loose notes and notebooks on various linguistic topics. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title, and then chronologically within each folder. The series is divided into four subseries that reflect the subject content of the notes: A. Cocopa, B. Yuchi, C. Yuman, and D. Other. The first subseries, Cocopa, includes notes on morphology and phoneme checking. The second subseries, Yuchi, includes notes on syntax and cognates to Siouan. The third subseries, Yuman, includes notes on phonemes and a notebook on Yuman reconnaissance. The fourth subseries, Other, includes notes and notebooks on Bakweri, Burmese, Cherokee, Choctaw, Korean, Mandingo, Shona, Shoshoni, and Wolof. There are also a number of unidentified notebooks. The earliest item is a manuscript Igorrote-English dictionary from 1906.
  - Series IV-A. Research Notes and Notebooks--Cocopa, 1962-1979
    - "Birds of the Southwestern Desert"--Cocopa, [1962] (Box Series IVA: B - Notebook #5)
    - "Cocopa "Animal Talk" ", n.d.
    - "Comparison of Cocopa, Maricopa, Diegueño, and Yavapai", 1964?
    - "Elements in Cocopa Vocabulary Probably Due to Culture Contacts with Western World", n.d.
    - Final Consonants Alphabetically Arranged, n.d.
    - Morphology (Noun), n.d.
    - Morphology (Verb), n.d.
    - Notebook
      -See Ser.IV-B, Notebook #9
    - Notebook #1, 1963
    - Notebook #2, 1963
    - Notebook #3, 1963
    - Notebook #4, 1963-1964
    - Notebook #5, 1964-1965
    - Notebook #6, 1965 (Box Series IVA: Notebook #6-14)
    - Notebook #7, 1965
    - Notebook #8, 1967
    - Notebook #9, [Part 1], 1967
    - Notebook #9, [Part 2], 1973
    - Notebook #10, 1978
    - Notebook #11, 1978
    - Notebook #12, 1978
    - Notebook #13, 1979
    - Notebook #14, 1979
    - Notebook #15, 1979 (Box Series IVA: Notebook #15 - R)
    - Notes #1, 1962
    - Notes #2, 1967
    - Notes #3, n.d.
    - Notes #4, n.d.
    - Phoneme Checking, n.d.
    - "Relativization and Nominalization in Cocopa", Jun. 1977
    - Songs, n.d. (Box Series IVA: S - W)
    - Spanish Words in Cocopa, n.d.
    - Syntax, n.d.
    - Word List, 1962
  - Series IV-B. Research Notes & Notebooks--Yuchi, 1970-1987
    General note
    Series IV-B: Research Notes & Notebooks--Yuchi
    - Handouts (Box Series IVB: H - Notebook #8)
    - Informants, n.d.
    - "Negation", n.d.
    - Notebook
      - Folders #1-4, Summer 1970
      - Folders #5-8, Summer 1971
      - Folder #9, Summer 1973 (Box Series IVB: Notebook #9 - Y)
        pp.1-28: Yuchi
        pp.31-86: Cocopa
      - Folder #10, 1987
    - Notes, n.d.
    - "Notes on Yuchi Syntax", 1978
    - "Possible Cognates to Yuchi in Siouan, Atakapa, Yava, Maider, etc.", 1971-1977
    - Rough Sheets, 1971
    - "Some Possible Cognates Between Yuchi and Siouan and Between Yuchi and Tunica", Jul. 1976
    - Yuchi Vocabulary by Seymour Frank, 1970
  - Series IV-C. Research Notes & Notebooks--Yuman, 1962-1985
    Series IV-C: Research Notes & Notebooks--Yuman
    - Notes, n.d. (Box Series IVC: N - Y)
    - "Notes on Possible Informants Among Speakers of the Yuman Language", n.d.
    - "Phonemes of Four Yuman Languages", 1962
    - Yuchi Data, [1985]
      -See also Oversized
    - Yuman Reconnaissance--Notebook, 1962
  - Series IV-D. Research Notes & Notebooks--Other, 1906-1988
    Series IV-D: Research Notes & Notebooks--Other
    - Alabama Vocabulary (Mary McCall), Oct. 1971 (Box Series IVD: A - Bam)
    - Bakweri--Notebook, 1981; 2 Folders
    - Bambara--Notebook, 1988
    - Basa--Notebook, 1984 (Box Series IVD: Bas - C)
    - Bayang; Hawaiian--Notebook, 1980
    - Biloxi-Ofo Bibliography, n.d.
    - Burmese--Notebook, n.d.; 2 Folders
    - Cambodian--Notebook, 1974-1975
    - Catawba, n.d.
    - Cherokee, NC Trip, May 1972
    - Cherokee--Notebook, 1972-1973
    - Cherokee Phonology, 1972
    - Chitimacha, n.d.
    - Choctaw--Notebook
      - Folder #1, 1971-1972
      - Folder #2, 1973
    - Columbus Museum, Jul. 1969
    - Dialect Study (El Centro, East Bay), 1964 (Box Series IVD: D - L)
    - Diegueño, n.d.
    - Haas Miscellany, 1980
    - Haas' Tunica Texts, n.d.
    - Havasupai, 1962
    - History of Linguistics, n.d.
    - Hokan Numerals, n.d.
    - Igorrote-English Dictionary--Notebook, [1906]
    - Japanese--Notebook, 1969
    - Kiliwa Word List, n.d.
    - Korean Notebook
      - Folder #1, 1967
      - Folder #2, 1971
    - Korean--Notes, 1967
    - Linguistic Atlas, 1964
    - Mandingo--Notebook, 1987; 2 Folders (Box Series IVD: M - Shon)
    - Maricopa Notes, n.d.
    - Maricopa Word Lists, 1962
    - Ma-Ya-Co-Ha Comparative Sets, 1964
    - Mikasula--Notebook, 1975
    - Miscellany, n.d.
      -See also Ser.V, Miscellany #3
    - "Mobilian Forms Collected August 27, 1970 from Leonard Lavan by J.M. Crawford Near Elton, Louisiana"
    - Mobilian Search--Notebook, 1976